Guide to the McConway and Torely Company Records, 1889-1945 AIS.1965.04
ULS Archives Service Center
McConway & Torely Company Records
1889-1945
AIS.1965.04
ULS Archives Service Center
3.75 linear feet (4 boxes)
The McConway and Torley Company began in Pittsburgh in 1869 designing train couplers. This collection contains historical information, photographs, brochures, scrapbooks, catalogs, publications, patent applications and patent examinations concerning the train coupler industry.
McConway & Torely Company.
Arrangement
Series I. History, 1945
Series II. Photographs, Atlantic City convention, 1947
Series III. Brochures, 1947
Series IV. Scrapbooks, 1891-1897
Series V. Catalogs, 1895-1948
Series VI. Publications, 1889-1943
Series VII. Patent Applications, 1905-1943
Series VIII. Patent Examinations, 1897-1924
Series IX. Plans, 1893-1906
History
The McConway and Torely Company partnership began in 1869 and played an integral role in the design and manufacturing of train couplers used to connect several train cars. While arriving in the city of Pittsburgh in the same year, 1849, the owners origins were quite different. William McConway Sr. was born in Ireland in 1843 and John J. Torely was born in New York City in 1830. During his life, McConway was involved in many diverse areas including Captain in the Union Army, Allegheny City Select Councilman, Trustee of Carnegie Tech, and was associated with Andrew Carnegie in the building of Carnegie Tech. This company designed, created and manufactured the state of the art Pitt Passenger Coupler which was operated successfully and used extensively on passenger equipment in service during the 19th century.
Scope and Content Notes
This collection covers the years of 1889-1945 and is arranged in nine series consisting primarily of historical information, photographs, brochures, scrapbooks, catalogs, publications, patent applications and patent examinations. Note that, plans in series IX are in microfiche format.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Donald L.Baughman, Manager of Engineering, McConway and Torley in 1965.
Existence and Location of Copies
Series IX is in Microfiche format.
McConway & Torely Company.; Business and Industry; Manufactures -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Railroad equipment industry -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Railroads -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Transportation
- History, 1945; I.
  - History, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Photographs, Atlantic City Convention, 1947; II.
  - Atlantic City Convention, Photographs, 1947 (Folder 2)
- Brochure, 1947; III.
  - Multiple-Load Truck, Brochure, 1947 (Folder 3)
- Scrapbooks, 1891-1897; IV.
  - Scrapbook, 1891-1892 (Box 1, Volume 1)
  - Scrapbook, Henry Romeike's Press Cuttings, 1892-1897 (Volume 2)
- Catalogs, 1895-1948; V.
  - M.C.B. Couplers, 1905 (Box 1, Volume 3)
  - The Janney Coupler, 1895, 1919 (Volume 4)
  - The Janney-Penn Coupler, Catalog C, 1919 (Volume 5)
  - Catalog and price list, Janney material (Box 2, Volume 1)
  - Draft for catalog, 1920 (Folder 1)
  - The Pitt Pivoted Passenger Coupler, 1920 (Folder 2)
  - Car Repairman's Guide, 1925 (Folder 3)
  - Multiple-load rail truck, drawings and advertisement in Railroad Equipment, 1948 (Folder 4)
- Publications, 1889-1943; VI.
  - The Evolution of Car Couplings, 1905 (Folder 5)
  - The Janney Radial Coupler, 1905 (Folder 6)
  - Muller vs. Janney. A statement of the Information of All Railroad Companies Using the Janney Coupler, Platform, and Buffers, 1889 (Folder 7)
- Patent Applications, 1905-1943; VII.
  - Patent, Volume 1-10, 1905-1943 (Box 3, Volume 1-10)
  - "Spring Support for Railway", 1939, 1941 (Folder 1-2)
  - Report on Patent Applications Aquired by Zimmerman Steele Co., 1942 (Folder 3)
  - 4WTA Report, June 19, 1943 (Folder 4)
- Patent Examinations, 1897-1924; VIII.
  - Patent Examinations, 1897-1924 (Box 4, Volume 1-12)
- Plans, 1893-1906; IX.
  - Plans, in Microfiche format, 1893-1906 (Microfiche-cabinet 1, Drawer 8)